{"tossups": [{"question": "Gareth Jones first reported on this event in the West, for which he was criticized by Walter Duranty. Robert Conquest claimed that this event was deliberate in his book<em> The Harvest of Sorrow</em>. This event was triggered in part by the creation of<em> solkhozy</em> and<em> kolkhozes</em>, as well as the basing of requisition quotas on the excellent 1931 harvest. The Law of Spikelets exacerbated this event by defining theft as taking even the smallest amount of grain. Stalin\u2019s agricultural policies caused, for the point, what devastating 1932-33 genocidal famine that killed millions of Ukrainians?", "answer": "<b> Holodomor</b> (prompt on descriptions of a Ukrainian famine before mentioned at the end of the tossup)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man, who John Adams once called \u201cthe oddest looking man in the world,\u201d supposedly remained a bachelor after his love interest, Molly Vining married a rector. A disagreement between George Read and Thomas McKean led to this man showing up to a meeting in muddied boots after a seventy-mile journey from Sussex County in his home state to Philadelphia. For the point, name this man whose late-night ride allowed him to break a tie and cast Delaware\u2019s decisive vote in favor of independence.", "answer": "Caesar<b> Rodney</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this battle, the<em> Atago</em> sank in Palawan Passage after a torpedo attack by the USS<em> Darter</em>. During this battle, the phrase \u201cthe world wonders\u201d was added to an encrypted message to throw o\u21b5codebreakers, but accidentally delivered to the American admiral; as a result of that and other miscommunications, Thomas Kinkaid\u2019s Seventh Fleet asked, but did not receive, help from Willam Halsey\u2019s Third Fleet during this battle. The first series of organized kamikaze attacks took place during, for the point, what October 1944 battle fought in the waters o\u21b5Luzon, the largest naval battle of World War II?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Leyte Gulf</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this novel, Gintz tries to convince a group of deserters to return to the army, but his speech instead causes his own guards to rebel as well. The protagonist of this novel is held captive by the philosophizing Liberius, who leads the Forest Brotherhood. A character in this book is nicknamed either \u201cexecutioner\u201dor \u201cshooter\u201d because of his brutality. The main character of this novel falls in love with Lara while serving as a physician during World War I. For the point, name this novel by Boris Pasternak.", "answer": "<b> Doctor Zhivago</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "Nineteen of these vessels, including the<em> Sylph</em>, were used by the firm Jardine, Matheson & Company. Hercules Linton was hired to construct one of the few surviving examples of these vessels for John Willis. Donald Kay was known for building several of these specific vessels, whose use declined after the Panic of 1857. The<em> Cutty Sark</em> is an example of one of these made via composite construction. The<em> Sovereign of the</em> <em>Seas</em> was one of these that set a record by reaching 22 knots. The growing tea trade spurred construction of, for the point, what 19th century ships, the fastest class of sailing ships?", "answer": "<b> clipper</b>s (prompt on (sailing) ships or similar answers) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One side of this war created defensive formations known as the Lines of Torres Vedras after the Battle of Talavera. This conflict led to the creation of regional administrations called juntas that were eventually replaced by the C\u00b4adiz Cortes. During this war, defeats at Vitoria and Salamanca undermined the rule of Joseph Bonaparte, who fought against an allied force led by the Duke of Wellington. For the point, name this part of the Napoleonic Wars fought over Iberian territory.", "answer": "<b> Peninsular</b> War (prompt on Napoleonic War(s))", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1982, Air Florida Flight 90 crashed into a bridge spanning this river, and another bridge crossing it at Point-of-Rocks was destroyed in a 1936 flood. One tributary of this waterway meets this river at Buzzard Point and is crossed by the 11th Street Bridges, near which the Bonus Army set up camp in 1932. A man-made Tidal Basin adjacent to this river is the site of the National Cherry Blossom Festival and the Je\u21b5erson Memorial. The Anacostia and Shenandoah Rivers flow into, for the point, what river that runs past Washington, D.C.?", "answer": "<b> Potomac</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This event was investigated by a commission headed by Aaron Perry. It was brought to light when Henry McComb leaked incriminating letters to the Sun newspaper after disagreeing with Oakes Ames, who had undersold stock to Congressmen. Schuyler [skyler] Colfax was removed as Vice-President on a Republican election ticket for taking bribes during this event, in which the namesake firm overcharged the Union Pacific Railroad. For the point, name this Grant administration scandal involving an American construction company with a French-sounding name.", "answer": "<b> Cr\u00b4edit Mobilier</b> scandal", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Rights established in this treaty\u2019s Article 9 were affirmed by a three-amendment protocol signed by Nathan Cli\u21b5ord and others. A reporter for the<em> New York Herald</em> named John Nugent was questioned by the Senate after he attained a leaked copy of this treaty. This treaty, which was negotiated by Nicholas Trist, forced one side to pay 15 million dollars for over 500,000 square miles of land, extending that side\u2019s southern border to the Rio Grande. For the point, name this 1848 treaty that ended the Mexican-American War.", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Guadalupe Hidalgo</b> (accept<b> Treaty of Peace, Friendship, Limits, and Settlement between the United States and the Republic of Mexico</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In the lead-up to this event, a newspaper published a racist reinterpretation of the Ten Commandments and repeatedly called undesirables \u201ccockroaches.\u201d Antonia Locatelli was executed for opposing this event, which was supported by propaganda from the RTML radio station. Over 1,000 people hid from this event in the Hotel des Mille Colinnes [mil koh-lin]. This event was sparked by the downing of Juvenal Habyarimana\u2019s plane and was carried out by Interahamwe paramilitary groups. For the point, name this 1994 mass killing of Tutsis by Hutus in a central African country.", "answer": "1994<b> Rwanda</b>n<b> Genocide</b> (prompt on partial answers; prompt on descriptive answers that use clues not yet read, like Tutsi, in place of \u201cRwanda\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Two answers required. One of these two people warned that a group is \u201cdetermined to foment a rebellion\u201d in a letter to the other, urging him to be \u201cmore generous and favorable to\u201d a certain group than his ancestors were. One of these two people asks the other not to place \u201cunlimited power into the hands of the husbands,\u201d as \u201call men would be tyrants if they could.\u201d The \u201cremember the ladies\u201d letter was one of hundreds of letters between, for the point, what married couple that moved into the newly constructed White House in November 1800?", "answer": "<b> Abigail</b> Adams<b> and John Adams</b> (accept<b> Abigail Smith</b> for<b> Abigail</b> Adams; prompt on\u201cthe Adams family\u201d or on Adams alone; prompt if only one person is named; prompt on partial answers like \u201cAbigail Adams and her husband\u201d) Page 3", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man betrayed his Italian allies by signing the Treaty of Monzon after his army captured the Valtelline valley. In order to fund his wars, this man raised the salt and land taxes and improved collection with a system of intendants. This man joined Sweden in the Thirty Years\u2019 War by signing the Treaty of B\u00a8arwalde, despite being Catholic. Marie de Medici tried to overthrow this man in the Day of the Dupes. For the point, name this mentor to Jules Mazarin, a cardinal who served as prime minister to Louis XIII [thirteenth].", "answer": "Cardinal<b> Richelieu</b> (or Armand Jean<b> du Plessis</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This composer set a W.H. Auden text consisting of four haikus in his<em> Elegy for J.F.K.</em>, and wrote a neoclassical piece in E-flat major titled for a Washington, D.C. estate that also hosted a 1944 conference that helped create the UN. This composer of the<em> Dumbarton Oaks Concerto</em> wrote a ballet featuring an\u201cInfernal Dance\u201d in which Prince Ivan destroys a magical egg that contains the soul of Kashchei the Immortal. For the point, name this composer who collaborated with Serge Diaghilev\u2019s Ballet Russes [roose] on<em> The Firebird</em>?", "answer": "Igor<b> Stravinsky</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In a skirmish fought near this body of water, American forces liberated the<em> Adams</em> and the<em> Caledonia</em>. Tensions arose between the U.S. and Great Britain when America deployed the<em> Michigan</em> on this body of water, violating standards established by the Rush-Bagot Treaty. Robert Barclay lost a battle fought in this body of water\u2019s inlet of Put-in-Bay; the winning commander of that battle declared \u201cWe have met the enemy and they are ours.\u201d For the point, name this body of water that names a victory for Oliver Hazard Perry in the War of 1812.", "answer": "Lake<b> Erie</b> (accept Battle of Lake<b> Erie</b>) Page 4", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A member of this family was nearly deposed in the August Faction movement. Another coined the term Arduous March for a famine that swept through his country. Leaders from this family have promoted the policies of<em> songun</em> and<em> juche</em> [joo-chay] to strengthen their military and promote nationalism. A late member of this family holds the title Eternal President, maintaining his position and status in this family\u2019s cult of personality. For the point, name this ruling family of North Korea.", "answer": "<b> Kim</b> family (accept the Mount<b> Paektu</b> Bloodline and similar descriptions)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In this book\u2019s second chapter, the central group defeats Sihon the Ammonite. Kidnapping and usury are among the crimes forbidden in this book\u2019s namesake \u201cCode,\u201d which is laid out by one speaker on the plains of Moab. This book\u2019s sixth chapter serves as the basis for the Shema prayer. This book\u2019s main speaker dies after ascending Mount Nebo and is then succeeded by Joshua. Moses delivers a series of sermons to the Israelites in, for the point, what final book of the Pentateuch and fifth book of the Old Testament?", "answer": "Book of<b> Deuteronomy</b> (accept<b> Deuteronomion</b>; accept<b> Devarim</b>; do not accept or prompt on Bible, Old Testament, or Pentateuch)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This battle is commemorated in a series of Mikhail Dudin-inspired monuments called the Green Belt of Glory. The Sinyavino O\u21b5ensive was initiated to support one side in this battle, though its planners were unaware that the other side had launched Operation North Light at the same time. Supplies were delivered via the Road of Life across the frozen Lake Ladoga during this battle, which began on September 8, 1941, and involved an encirclement by Army Group North. Millions of people died during, for the point, what 900-day siege of a Soviet city?", "answer": "Siege of<b> Leningrad</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In a sculpture by Barnett Newman, one of these structures supports a broken obelisk. The tomb of Gaius Cestius is shaped like one of these structures and located in Rome. A complex of these structures at Dashur includes atypical brick ones, as well as \u201cbent\u201d ones built from stone. The most famous examples of these structures were originally covered with reflective white limestone that only survives at the top of one of them, intended for Khafre. For the point, name these geometric structures used to house the tombs of Menkaure and Khufu.", "answer": "<b> pyramid</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Edict of Caracalla granted Roman citizenship to slaves in the empire and gave this man\u2019s name to all free men. During the reign of this man, a plague documented by Galen killed his co-ruler, Lucius Verus. This man died near modern Vienna as he campaigned against the Quadi as part of the Marcomannic Wars; during that campaign, he wrote a philosophical work on describing his Stoic philosophy. Commodus succeeded, for the point, which last of the Five Good Emperors, the author of<em> Meditations</em>?", "answer": "<b> Marcus Aurelius</b> Antoninus Augustus", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This figure is credited with developing the \u201crose diagram\u201d variant of the pie chart, which was used to describe deaths at the Selimiye [seh-lim-ee-yeh] Barracks. This figure convinced Isambard Kingdom Brunel to build the Renkioi facility after taking out a newspaper report on the inadequacy of the hospitals at Scutari. This figure, the only woman to appear in Lytton Strachey\u2019s<em> Eminent Victorians</em>, became famous during the Crimean War as the \u201cLady with the Lamp.\u201d For the point, name this British woman, the founder of modern nursing.", "answer": "Florence<b> Nightingale</b> Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "People operating in this location were asked \u201cAny of your guys wearing hippie clothes?\u201d by a man stationed in a Howard Johnson\u2019s Motor Lodge across the street. James McCord was arrested in this location after Frank Wills, a security guard, noticed that tape had been placed on a door latch a second time. Howard Hunt and Gordon Liddy planned that operation, which led to five arrests in this building complex on the Potomac River. For the point, name this Washington, D.C. office complex and hotel where the Democratic National Committee\u2019s headquarters were burglarized in 1972, starting a scandal that toppled Richard Nixon.", "answer": "<b> Watergate</b> (Complex, Hotel, and/or Office building; prompt on Washington, D.C. before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One member of this family ordered his Defense Brigades to massacre inhabitants of Tadmur Prison; that man from this family rose to power after overthrowing Salah Jadid. Bassel\u2019s death in a car crash led another son of Hafez to rise to the head of this family; that man is the current Alawite ruler of a country whose use of chemical weapons crossed President Obama\u2019s \u201cred line.\u201d For the point, name this Syrian ruling family currently led by Bashar.", "answer": "al-<b>Assad</b> family", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 1914, an arms ship bound for this country named the<em> Ypiranga</em> was illegally intercepted by an American warship. The Liberation Army of the South was a paramilitary group in this country, where the US occupied a port city for seven months after the Tampico A\u21b5air. The Plan of Ayala was proclaimed by a revolutionary whose base of power in this country was the state of Morelos. For the point, name this country where peasants were led by Emiliano Zapata and where, during World War I, the US occupied Veracruz.", "answer": "<b> Mexico</b> (or United<b> Mexican</b> States or Estados Unidos<b> Mexicanos</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man named present-day Guam the \u201cIsland of the Lateen Sails\u201d for the sheer number of prau vessels that approached his ship on his arrival there; that account was documented by Antonio Pigafetta, one of this man\u2019s crew. This colleague of Juan Elcano tried to convert Lapu-Lapu to Christianity, but failed; shortly after, Lapu-Lapu\u2019s men attacked and this man was struck with a bamboo spear, killing him. For the point, name this Portuguese explorer whose surviving crew then finished the first expedition to circumnavigate the Earth.", "answer": "Ferdinand<b> Magellan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A school of sociology that studied this city pioneered social disorganization theory. Ernest Burgess developed his concentric circle model for city development here.The \u201cfreshwater\u201d school of economics during the 20th century was based in this American city, as opposed to the \u201csaltwater\u201d schools based at Harvard and Berkeley. Milton Friedman was part of a group of monetarist economists based in this city\u2019s namesake university, located in Hyde Park. For the point, name this largest Midwestern city.", "answer": "<b> Chicago</b> (accept University of<b> Chicago</b>) Page 7", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "This ruler commissioned a cathedral dedicated to Saint Hedwig, the patron of his realm. This man hired Samuel von Cocceji to reform the laws of his kingdom, and he tried to expand his influence by creating the F\u00a8urstenbund to prevent the annexation of Bavaria. This patron of Voltaire cultivated the arts from his palace of Sanssouci. The death of Empress Elizabeth of Russia, known as the Miracle of the House of Brandenburg, saved this ruler from near-defeat during the Seven Years War. For the point, name this enlightened despot of 18th century Prussia.", "answer": "<b> Frederick the Great</b> (or<b> Frederick II</b> of Prussia) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man became navarch three years after a predecessor, Mindarus, died at the Battle of Cyzicus; while holding that post, he won a battle in which a ten-unit decoy force led by Antiochus fell apart after Antiochus was killed. This victor at the Battle of Notium blockaded a city to allow Pausanias to lay siege to it. He is best known for commanding one side to victory at a 405 BC battle in which Conon\u2019s fleet was quickly captured on a beach; that battle at Aegospotami brought an end to the Peloponnesian War. For the point, name this Spartan naval commander.", "answer": "<b> Lysander</b> (or<b> L\u00b4ysandros</b>) Page 8", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}], "bonuses": []}